<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two speeches made in the House of Peers the one November 20, 1675, the other in November 1678 / by a Protestant peer of the realm of England.</title>
            <author>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1621-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14731</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12429246</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12429246</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61934</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59486)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61934)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 297:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two speeches made in the House of Peers the one November 20, 1675, the other in November 1678 / by a Protestant peer of the realm of England.</title>
                  <author>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1621-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hague :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first speech is upon the appointing of a day for hearing Doctor Shirley's cause; the second is on the state and condition of England, Scotland and Ireland.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to the Earl of Shaftesbury. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Lords.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61934:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two Speeches Made in the HOUSE OF PEERS.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>The one</hi> November 20. 1675.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The other in</hi> November 1678.</item>
            </list>
            <p>BY A PROTESTANT PEER Of the REALM of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>HAGUE, Printed. 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:61934:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61934:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>E—</hi> of <hi>S—'s</hi> Speech in the Houſe of <hi>LORDS,</hi> upon the debate of appointing a Day for hearing Doctor <hi>Shirley</hi>'s Cauſe, <hi>20. November 1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OUr All is at ſtake, therefore you muſt give me leave to ſpeak freely before we part with it: My Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> is of Opinion, that we ſhould rather appoint a day to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what to do upon the Petition, than to appoint a day of Hearing; and, my Lord Keeper (for I may name them at a Committee of the whole Houſe) tells us in very eloquent and ſtudied Language, that he will propoſe us a way, far leſs liable to exception, and much leſs offenſive and injurious to our own Priviledg, then that of appointing a day of Hearing; and I beſeech your Lordſhips, did you not after all theſe fine words expect ſome admirable propoſal? But it ended in this, that your Lordſhips ſhould appoint a day, (nay a very long day) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what you would do in it. And my Lord hath undertaken to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you, that this is your only courſe by ſeveral undeniable reaſons, the firſt of which is, that it is againſt our Judicature to hear this Cauſe (which is not proper before us) nor ought to be relieved by us.</p>
            <p>To this my Lords give me leave to anſwer, that I did not expect from a man profeſſing the Law, that after an anſwer by order of the Court was put in, and a day had been appointed for Hearing (which by ſome accident was ſet aſide) and the Plaintiff moving for a ſecond day to be aſſigned, that ever without hearing the Councel on both ſides, the Court did enter into the merits of the Cauſe, and if your Lordſhips ſhould do it here, in a Cauſe attended with the circumſtances this is, it would not only be an apparent injuſtice, but a plain ſubterfuge to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord a point you durſt not maintain. But my Lords ſecond reaſon ſpeaks the matter more clearly, for that is, becauſe it is a doubtful caſe whether the Commons have not Priviledge? and therefore my Lord would have you to appoint a further day to conſider of it, which in plain Engliſh is, that your Lordſhips ſhould confeſs upon your Books, that you conceive upon ſecond thoughts, a doubtful caſe, for ſo your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61934:3"/>appointing a day will do, and that for no other reaſon, but becauſe my Lord Keeper thinks it ſo. I hope will not be a reaſon to prevail with your Lordſhips, ſince we cannot yet by experience tell that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is capable of thinking your Lordſhips in the right in any matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the judgment of the Houſe of Commons; it is too hard a thing for the ableſt of men to change ill habits: But my Lords, the reaſon is the moſt admirable of all, which he ſtiles unanſwerable, <hi>viz.</hi> That your Lordſhips are all convinced in your own Conſciences, that this if proſecuted will cauſe a breach: I beſeech your Lordſhips conſider whither this argument thus applied would not overthrow the Law of Nature, and all the Laws of Right and Property in the World; for it is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a very good one, that you ſhould not ſtand or inſiſt upon claims, where you have not a clear right, or where the Queſtion is not of conſequence, and of moment in a matter that may produce a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and pernicious breach between Relations, Perſons or Bodies Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick joyned in intereſt in high concerns together. So on the other hand if the obſtinacy of the party in the wrong ſhall be made an unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able argument, for the other party to recede and give up his juſt right; how long ſhall the people keep their Liberties, or the Princes the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of the World their Prerogative? How long the Husband main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Dominion, or any man his property, from his friends or neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours obſtinacy. But my Lords, when I hear my Lord Keeper open ſo eloquently the fatal conſequences of a breach, I cannot forbear to fall into ſome admiration how it comes to paſs, that if the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be ſo fatal, the Kings Miniſters in the Houſe of Commons (of which there are ſeveral that are of the Cabinet, and have daily reſort to His Majeſty) and have the Direction and Truſt of his Affairs. I ſay that none of thoſe ſhould preſs the conſequences there, or give the leaſt ſtop to the Career of that Houſe in this buſineſs, but all the Votes concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this affair; nay even that Vote that no Appeals from any Court of Equity is cognizable by the Houſe of Lords, ſhould paſs <hi>nemine contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diconte,</hi> and yet all the great Miniſters with us here, the Biſhops and other Lords of greateſt dependance upon the Court contend this point, as if it were <hi>pro noris &amp; foris.</hi> I hear His Majeſty in <hi>Scotland</hi> hath been pleaſed to Declare againſt Appeals in Parliament, and I cannot much blame the Court, if they think (the Lord Keeper and the Judges being of His Majeſties making, and of his Power to change) that the Juſtice of the Nation is ſafe enough, and I my Lords may think ſo to (during this Kings time) though I hear <hi>Scotland</hi> (not without reaſon) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain already; yet how future Princes may uſe this Power, and how
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61934:3"/>Judges may be made (not men of Ability and Integrity) but men of Relation and dependance, and who will do what they are commanded, and all mens Cauſes come to be Judged, and Eſtates diſpoſed of as Great men of the Court pleaſe. My Lords, the conſtitution of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hath provided better for us, and I can never believe ſo wiſe a Body as the Houſe of Commons will prove that fooliſh woman which pulls down her houſe with her own hands.</p>
            <p>My Lords, I muſt preſume in the next place to ſay ſomething to what was offered by my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> (a man of great Learning and Ability) and always verſt in a cloſer and ſtronger way of reaſoning, than the buſineſs of that Noble Lord I anſwered before, did accuſtome him to, and the Reverend Prelate hath ſtated the matter very fair on Two Heads.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, whether hearing of Cauſes and Appeals, and eſpecially in this point where the Members have priviledge, be ſo material to us, that it ought not to give way to the reaſon of State, and greater Affairs that preſs us at this time.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was, if this buſineſs be of that moment, yet whether the appointing a day to conſider of this Petition, would prove of that conſequence and prejudice to our Cauſe. My Lords, to this give me leave in the firſt place to ſay, that your Matter is no leſs than your whole Judicature, and your Judicature is the Life and Soul of your Dignity and Peer Right of <hi>England</hi> you will quickly grow burdenſome, if you grow uſeleſs, you have now the greateſt and moſt uſeful ends of Parliament principally in you, which is not to make new Laws, but to redreſs grievances, and to maintain the old Land mark. The Houſe of Commons buſineſs is to complain, your Lordſhips to redreſs, not only from them that are the Eyes of the Nation, but all other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons that Addreſs to you. A Land may groan under a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Laws (and I believe ours doth) and when Laws grow ſo mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed, they prove oftner ſnares than directions and ſecurity of the People; I look upon it as the ignorance and weakneſs of the latter Age (if not worſe, the effect of the deſign of ill-men) that it is grown a general Opinion, that where there is not particular direction in ſome Acts of Parliament, the Law is defective, as if the common Law had not provided much better, ſhorter and plainer for the peace and quiet of the Nation, then intricate long and perplext Statutes do, which hath made work for the Lawyers; given power to the Judges, leſſened your Lordſhips power, and in a good meaſure unhinged the ſecurity of the people. My Lord Biſhop tells you that your whole Judicature is not in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61934:4"/>queſtion, but only the priviledge of the Houſe of Commons, of their Members not appearing at your Bar: My Lords, were it no more yet for Juſtice and the peoples ſake, you ought not to part with it, how far a Priviledge of the Houſe of Commons, their Servants and thoſe they own doth extend, <hi>Weſtminſter Hall</hi> may with grief tell your Lordſhips and the ſame priviledge of their Members being not ſued, muſt be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your Lordſhips as well, and what a Salver of Juſtice you would prove whilſt they are Lords for Life, and you for Inheritance, let the World judge, for my part I am willing to come to a conference, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the diſpute ſhall begin again, and dare undertake to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips that they have neither Preſident, Reaſon nor any juſtifiable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to ſhow againſt us; and therefore my Lords, if you part with this your undoubted Right, meerly for asking where will this ſtop: And my Lords, we are ſure it doth not ſtop here, for they have already <hi>(nem ne contradicente)</hi> Voted againſt your Lordſhips power of Appeals from any Court of Equity, ſo that you may plainly ſee where this Caution and Reaſon of State means to ſtop, not on jot ſhort of laying your Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſide for the ſame reaſon of Paſſing the King money, of not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting good Laws (or what ever elſe) muſt of neceſſity avoid a breach upon what ſcore ſoever, and your Lordſhips plainly ſee the breach will be made upon your Judicature, as upon thoſe, ſo that when your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have appointed a day (a very long day) to conſider whether Dr. <hi>Shirleys</hi> Caſe be not too hot to handle, and when you have done the ſame for Sir <hi>Nicholas Staughton</hi> (whoſe Petition I hear is coming in) your Lordſhips muſt proceed to a Vote to lay all private buſineſs aſide for Six Weeks; for that Phraſe of private buſineſs hath obtained upon this laſt age, upon that which is your moſt publick duty and buſineſs, namely the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, and I can tell your Lordſhips be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Reaſon that leads to it, that I have ſome intelligence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying ſuch a Vote, for upon the ſecond day of our ſitting, at the riſing of the Lords Houſe, there came a Gentleman into the Lobby, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a very great Perſon, and asked in great haſte, are the Lords up, have they paſſed the Vote, and being asked what Vote, he anſwered of no private buſineſs for Six Weeks. My Lords, if this be your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſee where you are, if we are to Poſt from our Judicature for fear of offending the Houſe of Commons for Six Weeks; that they in the interim may paſs the Moneys, and other acceptable Bills, that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty thinks of Importment. There are too many Wiſe men of the Houſe of Commons to be laid aſleep, and to paſs all thoſe acceptable things; and when they have done, to let us be let looſe upon them,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61934:4"/>will they not remember this next time there is want of Money, or may they not rather be aſſured by thoſe Miniſters that are among them, (and go on ſo unanimouſly with them) that the King is on their ſide in this Controverſie, and when the publick buſineſs is over, our time ſhall be too ſhort to make a breach, or vindicate our ſelves in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And then I beg your Lordſhips, where are you after you have Aſſented; but the laſt Seſſion your Right of the Judicature ſo highly, even in this point and after the Houſe of Commons had gone ſo highly againſt you on the other hand, as to poſt up their Declarations and Remonſtrances upon <hi>Weſtminſter Hall</hi> Door, the very next Seſſion after you Poſt down the very ſame Cauſes, and not only thoſe but all Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature whatſoever. I beſeech your Lordſhips, will not this prove a fatal Preſident and Confeſſion againſt your ſelves. It is a Maxime and a Rational one among the Lawyers, that one Preſident where the Caſe has been conteſted, is worth a thouſand where there hath been no conteſt. My Lords, in ſaying this, I humbly ſuppoſe I have given a ſufficient anſwer to my Lord Biſhops two Queſtions, whether the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of a day to conſider what you will do with the Petition, which is of that conſequence to your Rights, that it is a doubtful Cauſe, and infinitely ſtronger than if it were a new thing to you never heard of before; for it is that very ſame caſe, and very ſame thing deſired in that Caſe that you formerly ordered, and ſo ſtrangely affected; ſo that upon time and all the deliberations imaginable, you declare your ſelves to become doubtful, and you put your ſelves out of your own hands into that Power you have no reaſon to believe on your ſide in this Queſtion. My Lords, I have all the duty imaginable to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and ſhould with all ſubmiſſion give way to any thing that he ſhould think of importance to his Affairs: But in this point, it is to alter the Conſtitution of the Government. If you are asked to lay this aſide, and there is no reaſon of State can be an Argument to your Lordſhips to turn your ſelves out of that Intereſt, you having the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Government. It is not only your concern that you maintain your ſelves in it, but it is the concern of the pooreſt men in <hi>England,</hi> that you keep your Station. It is your Lordſhips concern, and that ſo highly, that I will be bold to ſay, that the King can give none of requital or recompence for it. What are empty Titles, what is preſent Power or Riches, or a great Eſtate wherein I have no fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or firm Property. It is the Conſtitution of the Government, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that ſecures your Lordſhips, and every man elſe in what he hath. The pooreſt Lord, if the Birth right of Peerage be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61934:5"/>hath a fair proſpect before him for himſelf and his Poſterity. But the greateſt Title, with the greateſt preſent Power and Riches, is a mean Creature, and maintains this an abſolute Monarchy, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than by ſervile and low flatteries upon uncertain terms. My Lords, it is not only your Intereſt by the Intereſt of the Nation, that you maintain your Rights. For let the Houſe of Commons and Gentry think what they pleaſe, there is no Prince that ever Governs without a Nobility or Army, if he will, if you will not have one, you muſt have another, for the Monarchy cannot long ſupport, or keep it ſelf from tumbling into a Democratical Republick: Your Lordſhips and the people have the ſame Cauſe, and the ſame Enemies. My Lords, would you be in favour with your King, 'tis a very ill way to it, to put your ſelves out of a future capacity, to be conſiderable in his ſervice. I do not find in Story, or in modern experience, but that it is better, and a man is much regarded that is ſtill in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and opportunity to ſerve, then he that hath wholly deprived him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all for his Princes ſervice; and therefore declare that I will ſerve my Prince as a Peer, but I will not Deſtroy the Peerage to ſerve him. My Lords, I have heard of twenty fooliſh Models and Expedients to ſecure the Juſtice of the Nation, and yet to take this Right from your Lordſhips, as the King by his Commiſſion appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Commoners to hear Appeals, or that the Twelve Judges ſhould be the perſons, or the perſons ſhould be appointed by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which are all not only to take away your Lordſhips firſt Rights that ought not to be altered any more than any other part of this Government, but are in themſelves (when well weighed) ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. I muſt deal freely with your Lordſhips, theſe things could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have riſen in mens minds, but that there hath been ſome kind of provocation that hath given the firſt riſe to it. I pray my Lords forgive me, if upon this occaſion I put you in mind of committing divers, and the ſcardal of it. Thoſe droves of Ladies that attend all Cauſes, 'twas come to that paſs, that men even hired or borrowed of their friends handſome Siſters, or Daughters to deliver their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And yet for all this, I muſt ſay, that your Judgments have been Sacred, unleſs in one or two Cauſes, and thoſe are moſt to that Bench from whence I apprehend moſt danger. There is one thing I had almoſt forgot, which is the conjuncture of time, the thing upon which our Reaſon of State turns. And ſo my Lords, give me leave to ſay, if this be not a time of leiſure for you to vindicate your Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, you muſt never expect one; I could almoſt ſay, that the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61934:5"/>Harmony, good Agreement, and Concord, that is to be prayed for at moſt other times, may be fatal to us now. We owe the Peace of theſe two laſt years, and the diſ-ingagement from the <hi>French</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the Houſe differing from the Sence and Opinion of <hi>Whitehall.</hi> So at this time of all things in the World, this Nation hath moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to apprehend dangerous is a general Peace, which cannot now happen without very advantageous termes to the <hi>French,</hi> and diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> We are the Kings Counſellours, and if ſo, have right to differ and give contrary Counſels to thoſe that are neareſt about him: I fear the words advance a general Peace, I am ſure I would adviſe againſt it, and hinder it at this time by all the ways imaginable. I heartily wiſh, nothing from you may add Weight and Reputation to thoſe Councels that would aſſiſt the <hi>French.</hi> No money for Ships, nor preparations you can make perſonal aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance our Prince can have, can ſecure us from the <hi>French,</hi> if they are at leiſure: He is grown the moſt Potent of us all at Sea, he hath built Twenty four Ships the laſt year, and hath Thirty more in number than we, beſides the advantage that all our Ships are out of order, and his exquiſitely provided for, that every Ship hath its par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Store-houſe. It is incredible the money that he hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in making Harbours; he makes Nature it ſelf give way to the vaſtneſs of his expences. And after all this, ſhall a Prince ſo wiſe, ſo intent in his Affairs, be thought to make all this preparation to Sail over Land to fall upon the Back of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and to batter the Walls of <hi>Camaurkie;</hi> or is it poſſible he ſhould overſee his Intereſt in Seizing of <hi>Ireland,</hi> a thing ſo feazable to him. If he be Maſter of the Seas, as he certainly now is, and which when attained, gives all the Mediterranean, <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt India</hi> Trade, and renders him (both by Scituation and exact Harbours perpetual) Maſter of the Seas with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpute. My Lords, to conclude this point, I fear the Court of <hi>England</hi> is verily miſtaken in it; and I do not wiſh them the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Concurrence of the Kingdom, and this out of ſincere Loyalty to His Majeſty, and Love to my Nation.</p>
            <p>My Lords, I have one thing more to trouble you with, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure it's a Conſideration of the greateſt Weight and Concern, both to your Lordſhips, and the whole Nation: I have often ſeen in this Houſe, that the Arguments with ſtrongeſt Reaſons, and moſt convincing to the Lay Lords in general, have not had the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the Biſhops Bench, but that they have unanimouſly gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us in matters, that many of us have thought Eſſential and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61934:6"/>Rights. And I conſider that it is not poſſible, that men of great Learning, Piety and Reaſon, as their Lordſhips ſhould not have the ſame care of doing right, and the ſame conviction what is right upon clear reaſon offered, that other your Lordſhips have. My Lords, I muſt neceſſarily think we differ in Principles, and then it is very eaſie to apprehend what is the cleareſt ſence to men of my Principle, may not at all perſwade, or affect the Conſciences of the beſt men of a different one. I put your Lordſhips Caſe, as it is now plainly before us; my Principle is, that the King is King by the Law, by the ſame Law that the poor man enjoys his Cottage; and ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the concern of every man in <hi>England</hi> that hath his Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to maintain, and to defend to his utmoſt, the King in all his Lawful Rights and Prerogatives. And my Principle is alſo, that the Houſe of Lords, and the Judicature, and Rights belonging to it, are an Eſſential part of the Government eſtabliſhed by the ſame Law the King Governing and Adminiſtring Juſtice by his Houſe of Lords, and adviſing with both his Houſes of Parliament in all important matters, is the Government I own, am born under, am obliged to: If ever there ſhould happen in future Ages (which God forbid) a King Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by an Army without a Parliament, it is a Government I own not, am not obliged to, nor was born under. According to this Principle every honeſt man, that holds it, muſt endeavour equally to preſerve the frame of the Government in all parts of it, and cannot ſatisfie his Conſcience to give up the Lords Houſe for the Service of the Crown, or to take away the juſt Rights or Priviledges of the Houſe of Commons to pleaſe the Lords. But there is another Principle got into the World, My Lords, that hath not been long there, for Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> was the firſt Author that I remember of it, and I cannot find that the Jeſuits or any Clergy have owned it, but ſome of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Clergy of our Britiſh Iſles, it is with us, as it is new; ſo the moſt dangerous deſtructive Doctrine to any Government and Law that ever was: It is the firſt of the Canons publiſhed by the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation 1640. That Monarchy is of Divine Right; this Doctrine was then Preached up and maintained by <hi>Sibthorp, Munwering,</hi> and others, and of late years by a Book publiſhed by Doctor <hi>Sanderſon</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> under the name of Arch-Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and how much it ſpread among our Dignified Clergy is very eaſily known. We all agree, that the King and his Government is to be obeyed for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, and that the Divine Precepts require not only here but in all parts of the World obedience to Lawful Governours: But this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61934:6"/>Family are our Kings, and this particular frame of Government is our Lawful Conſtitution, and obligeth us, as belonging only to the particular Laws of our Country. This <hi>Laudean</hi> Doctrine, was that Root that produced the Bill of Teſt the laſt Seſſion, and ſome very perplext Oaths that are of the ſame nature with that, and yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by ſeveral Acts of this Parliament. In a word, if this Doctrine be true, our <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is of no force, our Laws are but Rules a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, during the Kings pleaſure: Monarchy of Divine Right cannot be bounded nor limited by humane Laws; nay what is more cannot ſound it ſelf, and all our claim of Right by the Law, or the Conſtitution of the Government, all the Juriſdiction and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of this Houſe, all the Rights and Priviledges of the Houſe of Commons, all the Properties and Liberties of the people, are to give away not only the Intereſt, but to the Will and Pleaſure of the Crown. And that the beſt and worthieſt of men (holding this Principle) muſt Vote to deliver up all we have, not only when reaſon of State, and the ſeparate Intereſt of the Crown requires it; but when the Will and Pleaſure (if known) would have it ſo; for thus muſt be a man of that Principle, as the only rule and means of Right and Juſtice: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Lords, you ſee how neceſſary it is, that our Principles be known, and how fatal it is to us all, that this Principle ſhould be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſpread any further.</p>
            <p>My Lords, to conclude, your Lordſhips have ſeen of what conſequence this matter is to you, and that the appointing a day to conſider, is, no leſs than declaring your ſelves doubtful upon ſecond, and deliberate thoughts, that you put your ſelves out of your own hands, no more than moral probability of having this Seſſion made a Preſident againſt you. You ſee your duty to your ſelves and the people, and that it is really the Intereſt of the Houſe of Commons (but may be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the Court) that you loſe the Power of Appeals: But I beg our Houſe may not be <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> but your Lordſhips would take in this Affair, a due courſe to preſerve your ſelves, and appoint a day this day three weeks for hearing Doctor <hi>Shirleys</hi> Cauſe, which is my humble motion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:61934:7"/>
            <head>A Speech made in the Houſe of <hi>PEERS,</hi> by the <hi>E—</hi> of <hi>S— November 1678.</hi> upon conſideration of the ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu are appointing of the conſideration of the State of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to be taken upon a Committee of the whole Houſe ſome day the next Week; I do not know how, well what I have to ſay may be received, for I never ſtudied, either to make my Court well, or to be popular, I always ſpeak what I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Dictates of the Spirit within me.</p>
            <p>There are ſome other conſiderations that concern <hi>England</hi> ſo neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that without them you will come far ſhort of ſafety and quiet at home.</p>
            <p>We have a little Siſter, and ſhe has no breaſt, what ſhall we do for our Siſter in the day when ſhe ſhall be ſpoken for; if ſhe be a Wall, we will build upon her a Palace of ſilver, and if ſhe be a Door, we will incloſe her with Boards of Cedar, we have ſeveral little Siſters without breaſts; the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtant Church, the two Kingdoms of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> The foraign Proteſtants are a Wall, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wall and Defence to <hi>England;</hi> upon it you may build Palaces of ſilver, glorious Palaces. The protection of the Proteſtants abroad, is the greateſt power and ſecurity the Crown of <hi>England</hi> can attain unto, and which can only help to give a Check to the growing greatneſs of <hi>France: Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are two Doors that let in, either good or miſchief upon us. They are much weakned by the Arttifice of our cunning Enemy; and we ought to incloſe them with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61934:7"/>Bords of Cedar: Popery and Slavery like two Siſters, go hand in hand, ſometimes one goes firſt, and ſometimes the other in a Door, but the other is always following cloſe at hand. In <hi>England</hi> Popery was to have brought in Slavery; in <hi>Scotland</hi> Slavery went before, and Popery was to follow. I do not think your Lordſhips, or the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament have Juriſdiction there, 'tis a Noble and Antient Kingdom, they have an Illuſtrious Nobility, a Gallant Gentry, a Learned Clergy, and an Induſtrious Worthy People; but yet we cannot think of <hi>England</hi> as we ought, without reflecting on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they are in, they are under the ſame Prince and influence of the ſame Favourites and Council, they are hardly dealt with, and can we that are the Richer expect better uſage? for 'tis certain that in all abſolute Government, the pooreſt Countries are always moſt favourably dealt with, when the Antient Nobility and Gentry there cannot enjoy their Royalties, their Shrevedoms, and their Stewarties which they, and their Anceſtors have poſſeſt for ſeveral Hundred years, but that they are now enjoyned by the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, to make Deputations of their Authority, to ſuch as are their known Enemies; can we expect to enjoy our <hi>Magna Charta</hi> long, under the ſame perſons and adminiſtrations of Affairs, if the Council there can Impriſon any Noble Man for ſeveral years, without bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to Tryal, or giving the leaſt reaſon for what they do, can we expect the ſame men will preſerve the Liberty of the Subject here? I will acknowledge that I am not well verſt in the particular Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this I do know, that all the Northern Countries, have by their Laws, an undoubted and inviolable Right to their Liberties and Properties; yet <hi>Scotland</hi> has out-done all the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Southern</hi> Countries, in having their Lives, Liberties and Eſtates Sequeſtred to the Will and Pleaſure of thoſe that Govern. They have lately Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and Haraſt the Richeſt and Wealthieſt Counties of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and brought down the Barbarous Hilanders to devour them, and this without almoſt a tolerable pretence to do it, but thoſe which deſign to procure a Rebellion at any rate, which as they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged it, was only prevented by the miraculous Hand of God, or otherwiſe all the Papiſts of <hi>England</hi> would have been Armed, and the faireſt opportunity given in the juſt time, for the Execution of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61934:8"/>that bloody and wicked deſign the Papiſts had, and it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any man that duly conſiders it to think other, but that thoſe Miniſters that acted there, were as Guilty in the Plot, as any of the Lords that are in queſtion for it.</p>
            <p>My Lords, I am forced to ſpeak this and plainer becauſe till the preſſure be fully taken off from <hi>Scotland,</hi> it is not poſſible for me or any thinking man to believe that good is meant, 'tis hear we muſt ſtill be upon our Guard, apprehending that the Principle is not changed at Court, and that thoſe men that are ſtill in place and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority have their influence upon the mind of our Excellent Prince, that he is not nor ever can be that to us which his Nature and goodneſs would incline him to: I know your Lordſhips can order nothing in this, but there are thoſe that hear me can put a perfect cure to it, and till that be done this <hi>Scotch</hi> weed is like Death in the Pot <hi>Mors in olla;</hi> But there is ſomething which now I conſider moſt immediatly concerns us, their Act of Two and Twenty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men to be ready to invade us upon all occaſions, this I hear the Lords of the Council there have treated (as they do all other Laws) expounded it unto a ſtanding Army of Sixty Thouſand Men. I am ſure we have reaſon and right to beſeech the King, that that Act may be conſidered in the next Parliament there. I ſhall ſay no more of <hi>Scotland</hi> at this time, I am afraid your Lordſhips will think I have ſaid too much having no concern there, but if a <hi>French</hi> Noble-man ſhould come to dwell in my Houſe and Family, I think it concerns me what he did in <hi>France</hi> for if he were there a Fellon, a Rogue, a Plunderer, I ſhould deſire him to live elſe where, and I hope your Lordſhips will think fit to do the ſame thing for your Nation, if you find the ſame cauſe.</p>
            <p>My Lords, give me leave to ſpeak Two or Three Words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our other Siſter <hi>Ireland.,</hi> thither I hear is ſent <hi>Douglaſſes</hi> Regiment to ſerve us againſt the <hi>French,</hi> beſides, I am credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Papiſts have their Armes reſtored, and the Proteſtants are not many of them received to favour being the ſuſpected Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Sea Towns as well as the In-lands are full of Papiſts: That
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61934:8"/>Kingdom cannot long continue in <hi>Engliſh</hi> hands if ſome better care be not taken of it.</p>
            <p>This is in your Power, and there is nothing there but is under your Laws; therefore I beg that this Kingdome at leaſt may be taken into your conſideration, together with the State of <hi>England,</hi> for I am ſure there can be no ſafety here, if thoſe doors are not ſhut up and made ſafe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
